<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Israeli Official Guilty of Sexual Misconduct</title>
    <meta content="01mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/world/middleeast/01mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myre, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Haim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmert, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katsav, Moshe (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Ramon, Haim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EEDC153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Israeli Official Guilty of Sexual Misconduct</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Israeli Official Guilty of Sexual Misconduct</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG MYRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myre, Greg</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli court convicts Haim Ramon, former Israeli justice minister, on charges that he forcibly kissed young female soldier; conviction sparks speculation that Prime Min Ehud Olmert would soon reshuffle his cabinet; Ramon resigned after he was indicted in Aug; his conviction comes week after Pres Moshe Katsav suspends himself for three months from his largely ceremonial post while prosecutors consider possible charges of rape and sexual assault; prosecutions of prominent figures on sexual misconduct charges were rare in Israel's macho culture until 1998 passage of sexual harassment law; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Israeli court convicted a former justice minister, Haim Ramon, on Wednesday of charges that he forcibly kissed a young female soldier in a highly publicized case that added to the aura of scandal surrounding the country's leadership.</p>
        <p>In the wake of the guilty verdict in the Tel Aviv Magistrate's Court, speculation was widespread that Prime Minister Ehud Olmert would soon reshuffle his cabinet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conviction of a former justice minister on charges that he forcibly kissed a young female soldier added to the aura of scandal surrounding the country’s leadership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Israeli court convicted a former justice minister, Haim Ramon, on Wednesday of charges that he forcibly kissed a young female soldier in a highly publicized case that added to the aura of scandal surrounding the country's leadership.</p>
        <p>In the wake of the guilty verdict in the Tel Aviv Magistrate's Court, speculation was widespread that Prime Minister Ehud Olmert would soon reshuffle his cabinet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramon resigned after he was indicted in August, and his duties were taken over by Foreign Minister Tzipi Livni on an interim basis. With Mr. Ramon's conviction, Mr. Olmert may seek broader changes in an attempt to re-energize his government, which has been dragged down by scandal and criticism of its handling of the war with Hezbollah in Lebanon last summer.</p>
        <p>The court ruled a week after the president of Israel, Moshe Katsav, suspended himself for three months from his largely ceremonial post while prosecutors considered possible charges of rape and sexual assault. The Justice Ministry says such charges are likely, but prosecutors have not decided. Mr. Katsav has left his official residence in Jerusalem and is living in southern Israel.</p>
        <p>Prosecutions of prominent figures on sexual misconduct charges had been rare in Israel's macho culture. But that changed in 1998 with the passage of a sexual harassment law. In recent years, several such cases have occurred, including the 2001 conviction of Yitzhak Mordechai, a former defense minister and transportation minister.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramon, 56 and divorced, was charged with kissing a 21-year-old soldier at a government office on July 12, the day the war between Israel and Hezbollah began.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramon said the woman flirted with him at an office gathering, and asked to have her picture taken with him. In court, Mr. Ramon's lawyers showed a photograph of the two hugging as they posed for the camera. In his testimony, Mr. Ramon also acknowledged the kiss, but said it was consensual.</p>
        <p>However, the soldier said that Mr. Ramon had kissed her against her will, and the three-judge panel concurred.</p>
        <p>''This was not a kiss of affection,'' said Judge Hayuta Kochan, who read the unanimous verdict. ''This has all the elements of sexual crime.''</p>
        <p>Photographers and video camera operators swarmed around a silent Mr. Ramon as he left the courthouse with his girlfriend. He is to be sentenced in about three weeks, though he said on Wednesday that he would appeal. He could receive a maximum sentence of three years, but Israeli legal commentators said they thought it was unlikely that he would be imprisoned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramon has been a legislator for more than two decades and was a leading figure in the center-left Labor Party.</p>
        <p>When the former prime minister, Ariel Sharon, abandoned his conservative Likud Party and created the centrist Kadima Party at the end of 2005, Mr. Ramon was among the Labor legislators who defected to join him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon had a stroke in January 2006, but the new party captured the Israeli parliamentary polls in March. Mr. Ramon was considered a confidant and important ally of Mr. Olmert.</p>
        <p>In another development, Mr. Olmert has asked security officials to examine the possibility of re-routing part of Israel's West Bank separation barrier to bring two additional Jewish settlements inside its walls, his office said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The newspaper Haaretz reported Wednesday that Mr. Olmert had already approved the change. But Mr. Olmert's office said he had only asked for a review, and on his own could not overturn the cabinet's decision on the route of the barrier.</p>
        <p>If the proposed route was ultimately approved, it would put about 20,000 additional Palestinians on the Israeli side of the barrier, according to the Haaretz report.</p>
        <p>Israel says it is erecting the barrier to protect against suicide bombings and other attacks. But much of the international community opposes it, and the International Court of Justice, in a nonbinding ruling in 2004, said parts built in the West Bank violated international law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
