<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Palo Alto Board Rejects Classes in Mandarin</title>
    <meta content="01palo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/us/01palo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mandarin Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Palo Alto (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DC153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Palo Alto Board Rejects Classes in Mandarin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Palo Alto Board Rejects Classes in Mandarin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <dateline>PALO ALTO, Calif., Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palo Alto, Calif, school district decides against plan for Mandarin language immersion, citing practical concerns as well as whether classes would give small group of students unfair advantage; plan prompted huge response in community that is about 17 percent Asian and where competition for slots in excellent public schools begins at kindergarten (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would have seemed to be a perfect fit: an academically ambitious plan for an ambitiously academic city.</p>
        <p>But after weeks of debate occasionally tinged with racial overtones, the Palo Alto Unified School District decided early Wednesday against a plan for Mandarin language immersion, citing practical concerns as well as whether the classes would give the small group of students in them an unfair advantage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Palo Alto Unified School District cited practical concerns for rejecting Mandarin language immersion as well as concerns the classes would give the small group of students in the classes an unfair advantage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would have seemed to be a perfect fit: an academically ambitious plan for an ambitiously academic city.</p>
        <p>But after weeks of debate occasionally tinged with racial overtones, the Palo Alto Unified School District decided early Wednesday against a plan for Mandarin language immersion, citing practical concerns as well as whether the classes would give the small group of students in them an unfair advantage.</p>
        <p>The proposal, which was voted down 3 to 2 after a marathon six-hour meeting of the district school board, would have established two classes taught mostly in Mandarin -- the world's most spoken language, used by nearly one billion Chinese -- to 40 kindergarten and first-grade students at a local elementary school.</p>
        <p>Grace Mah, a second-generation Chinese-American and the founder of Palo Alto Chinese Education, which lobbied for the program, said the vote was a major disappointment.</p>
        <p>''I think there's a number of people who are afraid of change,'' said Ms. Mah, a 46-year-old computer engineer and a mother of two, including a third-grader in Palo Alto schools. ''I think here's a number of people who don't believe in alternative education. And I think there's a number of people who insist on equity, when in life, it just isn't.''</p>
        <p>She added that her group might now try to start a charter school devoted to Mandarin.</p>
        <p>The plan had prompted a flurry of community response in Palo Alto, an affluent Silicon Valley hub 35 miles south of San Francisco, known as the home to Stanford University and as a place where competition for slots in its excellent public schools can begin in kindergarten. About 17 percent of Palo Alto's population is Asian, according to the most recent census statistics.</p>
        <p>The idea for a Mandarin immersion program was first floated here four years ago. The most recent plan was proposed to the board in December and then modified earlier this month. If approved, Palo Alto would have joined two other Bay Area cities with Chinese language immersion programs in schools. They are Cupertino, a Silicon Valley neighbor, and San Francisco, which has two Mandarin immersion programs and five in Cantonese, another Chinese dialect.</p>
        <p>And while Tuesday night's -- and Wednesday morning's -- debate was civil, two board members said they had received racially charged phone calls, e-mail messages and letters in the weeks leading up to their vote. One of the board members, Dana Tom, said he was upset by some of the comments, and surprised that they had come from a populace that prides itself on its sophistication.</p>
        <p>''I have higher hopes for our community, and yet, I'm not naïve,'' said Mr. Tom, who is Chinese-American and voted against the plan. ''Sadly, we're not past all of that.''</p>
        <p>Proponents of the program cast it as not only a valuable tool in the global economy, but also as a way for Palo Alto to lead the way for other California school districts.</p>
        <p>''We are in Palo Alto; we have the resources that other places don't,'' said Camille Townsend, the board president, who voted for the plan. ''When we say we can't do it here, it's like saying you can't do it anywhere.''</p>
        <p>But Ann Pianetta, whose 16-year-old son is a sophomore in Palo Alto and soon faces the college admissions tests, was among other parents who said the idea of some children having access to special programs struck them as undemocratic.</p>
        <p>''I'm all for foreign languages, but I think the delivery system is bad,'' said Ms. Pianetta, who started a volunteer after-school Japanese class for her son and other students. ''It deprives this education to all these other kids. A public school is supposed to be a public school.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
