<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Land of Lost Men, No One Asks for Direction</title>
    <meta content="01gitl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/books/01gitl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">LeDuff, Charlie</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">US Guys: The True and Twisted Mind of the American Man (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E4DD153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Land of Lost Men, No One Asks for Direction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Land of Lost Men, No One Asks for Direction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD GITLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gitlin, Todd</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>US Guys  The True and Twisted Mind of the American Man  By Charlie LeDuff  242 pages. Penguin Press. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Let us now profile superfluous men. Charlie LeDuff, a reporter for The New York Times, often writes about folks who claw and hang on by their fingernails. For his new book, ''US Guys,'' he spent a year roaming -- sometimes rambling -- through masculine America, mainly parts West and South. He hung out at a biker club, a gay rodeo, a circus, a snake-handler revival church, a male modeling agency and a Little Big Horn re-enactment among other sites of lowlife, high jinks and fall-downs. He has a taste for the legions of men who are known today, with a curl of the lip, as losers -- or, as he writes about a semipro football team in Amarillo, Tex., that he joins in homage to George Plimpton, ''dudes grasping at the frayed end of the rope of hope.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his trip through masculine America, Charlie LeDuff found a country of “dudes grasping at the frayed end of the rope of hope.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>US Guys  The True and Twisted Mind of the American Man  By Charlie LeDuff  242 pages. Penguin Press. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Let us now profile superfluous men. Charlie LeDuff, a reporter for The New York Times, often writes about folks who claw and hang on by their fingernails. For his new book, ''US Guys,'' he spent a year roaming -- sometimes rambling -- through masculine America, mainly parts West and South. He hung out at a biker club, a gay rodeo, a circus, a snake-handler revival church, a male modeling agency and a Little Big Horn re-enactment among other sites of lowlife, high jinks and fall-downs. He has a taste for the legions of men who are known today, with a curl of the lip, as losers -- or, as he writes about a semipro football team in Amarillo, Tex., that he joins in homage to George Plimpton, ''dudes grasping at the frayed end of the rope of hope.''</p>
        <p>Things are not going so well for the trapeze jockeys and race-track hangers-out, the outcasts and outraced rats, the ''have somewhats'' or ''the self-defeated, the people who fell off the table and are never getting up to the supper plate.'' They are living in places like the Shady Rest Court on Route 66 in Tulsa, Okla., for $65 a week, and a flophouse on the Bowery where, deep into a partying night, when the beds run out, you sleep in the bathtub. They are horny-handed, hornswoggled and just plain horny.</p>
        <p>Mr. LeDuff listens as they sputter with anger, slump into melancholia, live out ''the modern man's anxiety of not knowing exactly what a modern male should be.'' They are men in full strut and inaudible whimper. He commiserates, and refuses to patronize. Sometimes a homegrown Borat, he asks provocative questions and his subjects return the favor. He finds everywhere ''the same worries and uncertainties, the same preoccupations,'' namely ''race, sexuality, God, ambition, isolation, misunderstanding, fear.''</p>
        <p>He is no systematizer, but an observer as shrewd as he is alert, punctuating his road tales with aperçus like this on the weeklong Burning Man festival-slum held annually on the flats of Black Rock City, Nev.: ''So much ingenuity my generation has, and no place to put it.''</p>
        <p>Among the tens of thousands who gather to commit reckless acts of self-expression, he watches ''the drug-retching, the anguish, the screams, the howls, the good-looking girl slashing at her face with her own dirty fingernails'' and reflects ''that self-expression is dangerous when too much expression is mixed with too little sense of self.'' These freelance outcasts ''say things like, 'My culture's been stolen from me,' when what it really is, perhaps, is that you've thrown your culture away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. LeDuff's guys live in a world of posing, ambition, emptiness, and hurt, in a ''vast, hard country, where the promise of opportunity can murder you,'' and he claims the right to rub that world into the reader's face, partly because the men he finds are really there, lonely and dispossessed, and partly because he comes from them, having spent fight-club afternoons as a boy smashing and getting smashed by his brothers.</p>
        <p>His oddballs are not the quaint stuff of travelogues. They do not mainly triumph over adversity. They are sometimes unpleasant. Sometimes they (and even Mr. LeDuff himself) make the sensitive reader cringe, as, for example, when he drops the fact that he was ''busted for urinating in the public parking garage.'' There's a lot of raunch and stench in these pages, including not a few toilet observations, some of which were, to this reader at least, weirdly original. Mr. LeDuff might say he goes down and dirty because the American dream stinks nowadays of pure greed and craziness, and who's to say he's wrong?</p>
        <p>Mr. LeDuff has a distinct style for committing what the sociologist C. Wright Mills said was James Agee's forte: sociological poetry. But Mr. LeDuff is also a child of this age of apparently casual, sometimes reckless self-disclosure. At times the reader may think that Narcissus is mud-wrestling Agee, sometimes pinning him, sometimes getting pinned, neither of them coming out clean.</p>
        <p>But after a while it becomes plain that Mr. LeDuff has his reasons for stripping bare in public. He wants the reader to know that for a strutter, being damaged is normal. When he writes, ''In America, we are full of emotionally arrested men who take the mythology of reinvention, the notion of the individualist, and screw it all up,'' he wants you to look in the mirror.</p>
        <p>Mr. LeDuff has some Damon Runyon in him, some Raymond Chandler, and more good one-liners than a week's worth of machine-tooled sitcoms. On the vicinity of Oklahoma City: ''The landscape is so flat and barren you could probably watch your dog run away all day long.'' On a club where the customers are rural, Christian and gay: ''The drag-queen cowboys wore false eyelashes the size of tarantulas.'' On a Florida race-track diner: ''The joint reeks of arthritis rub and thin coffee.'' A Kentucky Derby-winning jockey ''was gold and then he was old and then he was wet laundry.'' Another man's face looked ''like a wet hanging sandbag.'' An overweight boy at a revival meeting ''looked like a cherub and an inmate.''</p>
        <p>All the inspirations to the contrary notwithstanding, Mr. LeDuff's an original. You want to quote him, intoxicated, maybe around the campfire, if you could find one nowadays in the part of town where the strip malls and the franchise fast-food joints sprawl.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES Todd Gitlin, a professor of journalism and sociology at Columbia University, is the author of 11 books, including ''The Intellectuals and the Flag.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Todd Gitlin, a professor of journalism and sociology at Columbia University, is the author of 11 books, including ''The Intellectuals and the Flag.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
