<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Pins and Needles, but Not Missing a Stitch</title>
    <meta content="01Online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/fashion/01Online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sewing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sewing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sewing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DD153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Pins and Needles, but Not Missing a Stitch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Pins and Needles, but Not Missing a Stitch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla column on pursuing her obsession with sewing online; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I NEVER expected to have fond memories of the fringed throw pillow that I had to sew to pass Home Economics.</p>
        <p>In fact I never expected to have any sort of voluntary memory of my early sewing class experiences after spending so many years trying to repress recollections of being in that last wave of girls, in the '70s, who were expected to master the domestic arts in school. (Hence, the ill-fitting corduroy wrap skirt I made after finishing the pillow.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mother’s innocent home project becomes an obsession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I NEVER expected to have fond memories of the fringed throw pillow that I had to sew to pass Home Economics.</p>
        <p>In fact I never expected to have any sort of voluntary memory of my early sewing class experiences after spending so many years trying to repress recollections of being in that last wave of girls, in the '70s, who were expected to master the domestic arts in school. (Hence, the ill-fitting corduroy wrap skirt I made after finishing the pillow.)</p>
        <p>Then I swore off sewing. Forever. So three decades later, as sewing has become a trendy hobby among younger enthusiasts who never were subjected to the tyranny of Home Ec, I'm surprised to find myself among those who are taking it up.</p>
        <p>''Taking it up'' is an understatement.</p>
        <p>I am obsessed.</p>
        <p>It started innocently enough, after my 9-year-old daughter recently asked if it was possible to sew a poncho for her doll. One thing led to another and in a matter of weeks, I went from being a rational person with a scrap of fabric and some thread to a crazed hobbyist with a borrowed electronic sewing machine capable of making 30 different stitches and automatic buttonholes.</p>
        <p>Of course, I'm not getting anything else done. Work is piled up. Laundry is piled up. The bills are piled up. I am not returning phone calls.</p>
        <p>But who cares? All that really interests me is figuring out how to get the lining to lie flat on a doll-size pleated skirt. (I can make pleats!)</p>
        <p>The problem, however, is that one corner of my office has a table covered with a mess of fabric, spools, pins and patterns. I can't find the scissors. How can I ever tackle a bigger project -- curtains, a tablecloth, matching napkins -- without the proper equipment?</p>
        <p>I phoned the Home Sewing Association for advice.</p>
        <p>''Good for you,'' said Karen Koza, a spokeswoman for the association. ''You've got the bug. Now you need to figure out how to keep all your things together, organized.''</p>
        <p>''First, maybe I should figure out why I'm so obsessed,'' I said. ''Why do I get so much satisfaction from sewing bits of fabric together with really, really straight seams?''</p>
        <p>''You get a feeling of mastery from making something,'' Ms. Koza said.</p>
        <p>''But I'm not a member of the crafty, do-it-yourself generation that sees sewing as an expression of personal creativity,'' I said. ''I was raised to think sewing, along with ironing and scrubbing floors, was a symbol of domestic repression.''</p>
        <p>''Don't forget that sewing was something that once was considered an essential life skill,'' Ms. Koza said. ''You are independent when you can make something of your own.''</p>
        <p>When she put it that way, I almost felt courageous for neglecting my work, the laundry and the bills. I wasn't spending all my time making tiny doll clothes -- no, I was learning a life skill.</p>
        <p>''What should I make next?'' I asked. ''Am I ready to tackle something human-size?''</p>
        <p>''Take something you already have in the closet, say the dirndl skirt from last season, and make it into this season's bubble skirt,'' Ms. Koza suggested. ''You can be creative and do what you want to it.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not that type,'' I said. ''I like to pattern. I like to cut out the little tissue-paper pieces.''</p>
        <p>''It's about starting small,'' Ms. Koza said. ''And going from there.''</p>
        <p>Even starting small, I would need basic supplies. So I visited the Home Sewing Association's Web site at Sewing.org, where I found a comprehensive list of necessities that included everything from an iron and ironing board to a strawberry pincushion. I already had a seam ripper, a measuring tape and pinking shears. But a bodkin to thread elastic through a casing? Who has a bodkin?</p>
        <p>I also glanced at some of the photos that visitors had posted in the ''My Sewing Room'' section, photos that showed sewing spaces that ranged from makeshift to swanky, with elaborate cutting tables (for a selection, see Sewingtableshop.com) and expensive computerized sewing machines from manufacturers like Bernina, whose top-of-the-line Arista 730e model has a suggested retail price of $7,999. (The model is described but not sold online at the company's Web site at Berninausa.com.) It is the sewing machine equivalent of a sports car. I phoned Jeanne Delpit, a spokeswoman for Bernina, in the hope that she would tell me I absolutely needed a sewing machine that automatically regulated zigzag stitches at variable lengths, was capable of making 850 different stitches, had three thread cutters, could sew in 16 directions and was powered by the Microsoft Windows operating system.</p>
        <p>''I'm making doll clothes,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''We have a nice little entry-level machine in our Bernette line,'' Ms. Delpit said. ''The line sells for from $399 to $749.''</p>
        <p>I looked at the little robe sitting on the table next to my borrowed sewing machine and realized that she had a point. Maybe I should master the art of sewing an under collar to a lining before investing my retirement savings in a sewing machine.</p>
        <p>''You can always trade up,'' Ms. Delpit said. ''We encourage customers to work with one of our authorized dealers, and if you take it back in six months and say, 'I want more,' they'll help.''</p>
        <p>I started small. I went shopping at sewing supply sites like Clotilde.com (where I bought a Magenta-Magic erasable pen, $5) and Junetailor.com (where I bought a thread rack that holds 60 spools, $18.99). I visited Reprodepot.com (where I gazed longingly at the fabrics) and Sewingpatterns.com (which carries a broad selection from dozens of manufacturers like Vogue, Simplicity and McCall's).</p>
        <p>Joannfabrics.com had a selection of basics, including four kinds of bodkins, for $1.60 to $2.99, not to mention 16 kinds of pincushions, at prices of $1.29 to $8.99. The Joann site also had a store locator; I typed in my ZIP code and learned that the company had four bricks-and-mortar stores within 30 miles.</p>
        <p>Should I drive to one? I looked at a stack of unopened mail on my desk. Then I looked at the doll-size robe. It needed piping. How do you sew on piping? I wasn't sure. But it was a life skill. The mail could wait.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail: slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
