<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outdoor Home Heater Makers Agree to Pollution Cutbacks</title>
    <meta content="01wood" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/nyregion/01wood.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070203T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1822949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boilers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoke</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, Anahad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DC153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outdoor Home Heater Makers Agree to Pollution Cutbacks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Outdoor Home Heater Makers Agree to Pollution Cutbacks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANAHAD O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Connor, Anahad</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency says 10 of top manufacturers of outdoor wood-burning boilers have agreed to start making cleaner and more efficient machines; devices, which were invented to heat farmhouses, have become fast-growing alternative among suburban homeowners, whose neighbors often complain that they produce unbearable levels of smoke; under agreement, manufacturers will produce models that are 70 percent cleaner (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten of the top manufacturers of a popular wood-burning device that reduces home heating costs but releases high levels of pollutants have agreed to start making cleaner and more efficient machines, the Environmental Protection Agency announced this week.</p>
        <p>The devices, invented to heat farmhouses, have become a fast-growing alternative among suburban homeowners. But the owners' neighbors often complain that the outdoor wood-fired boilers produce unbearable levels of smoke, and a growing body of research about the boilers' pollution has prompted campaigns around the country to limit their use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The devices, invented to heat farmhouses, have become a fast-growing alternative among suburban homeowners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ten of the top manufacturers of a popular wood-burning device that reduces home heating costs but releases high levels of pollutants have agreed to start making cleaner and more efficient machines, the Environmental Protection Agency announced this week.</p>
        <p>The devices, invented to heat farmhouses, have become a fast-growing alternative among suburban homeowners. But the owners' neighbors often complain that the outdoor wood-fired boilers produce unbearable levels of smoke, and a growing body of research about the boilers' pollution has prompted campaigns around the country to limit their use.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, the 10 manufacturers, which produce about 80 percent of the boilers on the market, will begin selling models this spring that are 70 percent cleaner and will carry orange tags saying they create less pollution.</p>
        <p>The manufacturers will also continue to offer the old-style models as well, said Leslie Wheeler, a spokeswoman for the Hearth, Patio and Barbecue Association, an industry group in Virginia that represents 8 of the 10 manufacturers. She said it was unclear whether the newer, more efficient models would cost more.</p>
        <p>John Millett, a spokesman for the environmental agency, said on Monday that the 10 manufacturers agreed to produce the new machines without regulatory pressure. The agency had considered establishing emissions standards, he said, but many of the states receiving high levels of complaints about the machines were unwilling to wait the year or more that the federal regulatory process might take.</p>
        <p>The agency also announced that it had developed guidelines that states and local governments could use to regulate the old boilers.</p>
        <p>''This is an important first step in getting a handle on a relatively new machine that's having an impact on air quality,'' Mr. Millett said.</p>
        <p>In the last two years, outdoor wood boilers have doubled in number, to about 150,000 nationwide. They look like tool sheds topped by 12-foot smoke stacks, and work by burning wood to heat water that is pumped through underground pipes to a home's plumbing and heating systems. Generally, they cost about $5,000.</p>
        <p>Owners of the machines say they handle almost all their home heating needs. They burn large amounts of wood and smolder constantly, though, and studies show that they also produce about a dozen times more smoke than traditional indoor stoves. One report by the New York attorney general's office found in 2005 that they produced as much particle pollution in an hour as 45 cars or 2 heavy-duty diesel trucks.</p>
        <p>As a result, a rash of lawsuits have been filed against those using the boilers, and many communities, mostly in the Northeast and Midwest, have passed ordinances regulating them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wheeler, the spokeswoman for the Hearth, Patio and Barbecue Association, said her organization would continue to work with the agency to make cleaner machines. She said the new agreement was only one phase of that process.</p>
        <p>''It's a great step forward toward improving the product,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 3, 2007, Saturday  Because of an editing error, an article on Thursday about an agreement by 10 manufacturers of outdoor wood-fired boilers to make cleaner and more efficient machines misstated the day that a spokesman for the Environmental Protection Agency commented on the agreement. It was Tuesday, not Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 3, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Thursday about an agreement by 10 manufacturers of outdoor wood-fired boilers to make cleaner and more efficient machines misstated the day that a spokesman for the Environmental Protection Agency commented on the agreement. It was Tuesday, not Monday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
