<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Execution, If It Occurs, Is Years Off For Killer</title>
    <meta content="01next" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Ronell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nemorin, James V (Detective)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Rodney J (Detective)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brick, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6DA153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Execution, If It Occurs, Is Years Off For Killer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ronell Wilson may stay in Brooklyn jail cell for years as his lawyers go through slow, complex and unpredictable process of appealing his conviction and death sentence for murder of two police detectives on Staten Island in March 2003; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ronell Wilson sits alone in a prison cell near Gowanus Bay in Brooklyn. He has been on suicide watch since his return late Tuesday evening from federal court in Brooklyn, where a jury called for his execution.</p>
        <p>''He's holding up well,'' said one of his lawyers, Ephraim Savitt, ''under the circumstances.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ronell Wilson sits alone in a prison cell near Gowanus Bay in Brooklyn. He has been on suicide watch since his return late Tuesday evening from federal court in Brooklyn, where a jury called for his execution.</p>
        <p>''He's holding up well,'' said one of his lawyers, Ephraim Savitt, ''under the circumstances.''</p>
        <p>On federal death row, he will join 46 other inmates, their cases in varying stages of appeal. If the sentence is carried out one day, Mr. Wilson, 24, will probably die by lethal injection at the federal death chamber in Terre Haute, Ind., where Timothy J. McVeigh, who bombed the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building in Oklahoma City, and two Texans have preceded him. But Mr. Wilson's lawyers said he will appeal his sentence, an unpredictable and complicated process that could take years.</p>
        <p>No other federal trial in New York has produced a death sentence in half a century. Three men have been put to death in federal cases since 1988, when a moratorium on federal capital punishment was lifted. Of these, the two Texans -- Juan Raul Garza, convicted of three drug-related murders, and Louis Jones Jr., convicted of rape and murder -- were each on death row for about eight years. Mr. McVeigh, who abandoned his appeals after being denied a stay of execution, was executed four years after his sentencing for the bombing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson was convicted of 10 crimes in December, chief among them the murder of two undercover detectives during a gun transaction on Staten Island in March 2003. Judge Nicholas G. Garaufis, who was not in his chambers yesterday, must set a formal sentencing date, according to his staff.</p>
        <p>On five counts, the judge is bound by the jury's verdict to impose death sentences. But for the other charges, including robbery conspiracy, attempted robbery and use of a firearm, the judge must determine prison terms. Some of the crimes are relatively minor, on the scale of regular business for a federal court in New York City.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson, for example, was found guilty of planning to rob a clothing store called Oz, near the Stapleton Houses on Staten Island, where his gang was based. The plan, to get a U-Haul truck and cart off the merchandise in broad daylight, was abandoned in the talking phase.</p>
        <p>The law calls for a presentence investigation, in which probation officers will interview Mr. Wilson to ascertain his background and present demeanor. They will compile a report for the judge, though it would seem he has already heard every imaginable aspect of Mr. Wilson's biography recounted in the courtroom during the penalty phase of the trial.</p>
        <p>''It's a charade at this point,'' Mr. Savitt said.</p>
        <p>Department of Justice officials said that after sentencing, Mr. Wilson will be assigned to a prison.</p>
        <p>The choice would seem to be foregone. All federal condemned prisoners are assigned to the United States Penitentiary in Terre Haute, said Felicia Ponce, a spokeswoman for the Bureau of Prisons. According to the Death Penalty Information Center, a private group that tracks capital cases, that institution was modified in 1995 to include an execution chamber and was converted to a death row center in 1999.</p>
        <p>Declining to address Mr. Wilson's case in particular, Ms. Ponce said that all inmates, including those bound for death row, are evaluated according to a point system to determine their assignment. So prison officials will study the seriousness of his offense, his criminal record, his projected length of imprisonment and earlier prison sentences. According to bureau policy statements, this process will involve two managers and a counselor, and perhaps an education adviser and a psychology services representative.</p>
        <p>Federal marshals will take Mr. Wilson to his assigned facility. He may join other inmates on an airplane, or he may be assigned to a private flight, said Ralph Rosado, a spokesman for the United States Marshals Service in the Eastern District of New York.</p>
        <p>''It's very new,'' Mr. Rosado said. ''I'm not sure.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson's lawyers must also confront the grim novelty of the circumstances.</p>
        <p>''The lawyers went out to an Irish pub,'' Mr. Savitt said, adding that he had trouble sleeping nonetheless. With the realm of possible motions in this trial exhausted, he said, the next forum for the case is appellate court.</p>
        <p>Upon formal sentencing, a convict has 10 days to file a notice of appeal, said Erik Ablin, a spokesman for the Department of Justice. From there, a briefing schedule would be established. After avenues of appeal have been exhausted, meaning the case has been declined by the United States Supreme Court, a prisoner could apply for relief from the court that imposed the sentence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Savitt said that grounds for appeal could include the judge's rejection of defense lawyers' efforts to eliminate certain members of the jury, including the foreman. He said the foreman had muttered and rolled his eyes during the closing defense argument.</p>
        <p>Other grounds could include the judge's decision to bar testimony on the nature of rap lyrics. Prosecutors had submitted handwritten lyrics they portrayed as a confession, and defense lawyers had hoped to call an expert to depict the lyrics as fantasies.</p>
        <p>Should all the appeals fail, Justice Department officials said, the Bureau of Prisons would set an execution date. An example of how that works is available from the case of Bruce Carneil Webster, another Texan, who was convicted of kidnapping resulting in death.</p>
        <p>Mr. Webster, who was sentenced to death in 1996, was notified in writing on Dec. 5, 2006, that he would be executed by lethal injection at 7 a.m. on April 16, 2007.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson's lawyers said they would ask court and prison officials to keep him in the cell in Brooklyn during the next stage of the process.</p>
        <p>''We have to consult with him on the appeal,'' Mr. Savitt said. ''This is his life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
