<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Griese Family to Al Capone, Secret Service Was on the Menu</title>
    <meta content="01nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/sports/football/01nfl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joe's Stone Crab (Miami Beach, Fla)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indianapolis Colts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Bears</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crouse, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griese, Brian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Chicago Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bears</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Joe's Stone Crab</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Griese, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDB153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Griese Family to Al Capone, Secret Service Was on the Menu</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Restaurant Helps N.F.L. Diners Keep a Low Profile</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Bears backup quarterback Brian Griese takes team to favorite Miami (Fla) restaurant Joe's Stone Crab before facing Indianapolis Colts in Super Bowl (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Brian Griese, the Bears' backup quarterback, was a child, Joe's Stone Crab in Miami Beach was like his dining room away from home. He frequently ate there with his father, Bob, the Dolphins' Hall of Fame quarterback, so of course it was the first place he thought to bring some of his teammates for dinner.</p>
        <p>''They all said it was the best stone crabs they've ever had,'' said Griese, who also recommends the fried shrimp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although they know Bears quarterback Brian Griese by name, the people at Joe’s Stone Crab do not to use it when calling his party, a habit that extends back to Bob Griese’s playing days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Brian Griese, the Bears' backup quarterback, was a child, Joe's Stone Crab in Miami Beach was like his dining room away from home. He frequently ate there with his father, Bob, the Dolphins' Hall of Fame quarterback, so of course it was the first place he thought to bring some of his teammates for dinner.</p>
        <p>''They all said it was the best stone crabs they've ever had,'' said Griese, who also recommends the fried shrimp.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, which has been open for 95 years, is like Griese's hometown version of ''Cheers.'' Griese said the maître d' who greeted him this week was a busboy when he started going to the restaurant. And there were plenty of other familiar faces among the wait staff.</p>
        <p>Although they know Griese by name, the people at Joe's are careful not to use it when calling his party for seating, a habit that extends back to the elder Griese's playing days.</p>
        <p>Bob Griese had an alias that he used in an effort to avoid attracting the attention of his fellow diners (so, according to restaurant lore, did the mobster Al Capone, who used the nom de guerre Al Brown).</p>
        <p>Griese told the story of when a new maître d', who was not familiar with the family alias, once called the Grieses to their table by name and set off a stampede of autograph hounds. Laughing, Griese recalled, ''We had to tell him, 'No, don't call us that.' ''</p>
        <p>The alias, which the Grieses use to this day, is the name of a street where the family once lived.</p>
        <p>NO CURVEBALLS -- Tommy John, the former major league pitcher, is the father-in-law of the Bears' long snapper, Patrick Mannelly. While watching Mannelly perform during the Bears' second-round playoff victory against Seattle, John, who recently became the manager of the Bridgeport (Conn.) Bluefish of the Atlantic League, found himself donning his scouting cap.</p>
        <p>After observing the deftness with which Brad Maynard, the Bears' punter and holder, handled a high snap from Mannelly on Robbie Gould's game-winning 49-yard field goal, John asked Mannelly for Maynard's telephone number.</p>
        <p>''Maynard has some of the best hands I've ever seen,'' John said Wednesday in a telephone interview. ''With those soft hands and quick feet, I wanted to invite him to be our shortstop.''</p>
        <p>John was joking, but the role of holder is no laughing matter. That was painfully evident in the first round of the playoffs when Dallas quarterback Tony Romo bobbled the snap on a possible game-winning field-goal attempt at Seattle.</p>
        <p>Maynard said he was watching the Cowboys' game against Seattle when Romo mishandled the snap, aborting the attempt with just over a minute to play.</p>
        <p>''My mouth dropped,'' he said. ''All of a sudden you go from we are going to be playing Dallas to we're going to be playing Seattle again. I felt bad for him. That has got to be the worst feeling in the world. I can't imagine it.''</p>
        <p>COWBOYS TAKING SOME TIME -- The Cowboys said they would not name Bill Parcells's replacement until after the Super Bowl. In his first public comments since Parcells retired Jan. 22, Jerry Jones, the team's owner and general manager, said Wednesday that he would not have a decision on a new coach until next week. Jones has interviewed eight candidates and may add to that list. (AP)</p>
        <p>McNABB WANTS TO STAY -- Donovan McNabb said he did not want to leave Philadelphia, was not jealous over the success Jeff Garcia had replacing him as Eagles quarterback, and was not muzzled by Coach Andy Reid. ''The so-called rumors that have started, they're false,'' McNabb said Wednesday. ''I'm a Philadelphia Eagle and will continue to be a Philadelphia Eagle, hopefully, for more years to come, and hopefully will retire as an Eagle.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>ALL IN THE FAMILY -- Brothers will officiate in the Super Bowl for the first time Sunday, with the umpire Carl Paganelli and the back judge Perry Paganelli working the game. (AP)</p>
        <p>AROUND THE LEAGUE -- The Hall of Famer Fred Biletnikoff retired as the Oakland Raiders' wide receivers coach after spending more than three decades as a player and coach for the franchise.  Chargers linebacker Steve Foley has sued the city of Coronado, Calif., and the off-duty police officer who shot him three times outside his home, accusing the rookie officer of negligence and excessive force. Foley was shot early Sept. 3 by a 23-year-old Coronado police officer who suspected him of drunken driving. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
