<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Another Struggle to Score, Shanahan Speaks Up for Jagr</title>
    <meta content="01rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/sports/hockey/01rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Maple Leafs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinser, Lynn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Toronto Maple Leafs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Maple Leafs</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Raycroft, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDA153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Another Struggle to Score, Shanahan Speaks Up for Jagr</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Another Struggle to Score, Shanahan Speaks Up for Jagr</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Toronto Maple Leafs defeat New York Rangers, 2-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan could have chalked up last night's game as a well-played 2-1 loss to Toronto, one blip in a long season, decided by a couple of bounces.</p>
        <p>To Shanahan, it was just another game. It was one more night when an opponent does everything but hogtie Jaromir Jagr, the Rangers' captain and leading scorer, and goes unpenalized. Shanahan said he had seen it so much this season that it was time to speak up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For much of the Rangers’ season, they have relied almost exclusively on Jaromir Jagr’s line for their scoring. During games like Wednesday night’s, when Jagr’s line is shut down, the Rangers struggle to score.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan could have chalked up last night's game as a well-played 2-1 loss to Toronto, one blip in a long season, decided by a couple of bounces.</p>
        <p>To Shanahan, it was just another game. It was one more night when an opponent does everything but hogtie Jaromir Jagr, the Rangers' captain and leading scorer, and goes unpenalized. Shanahan said he had seen it so much this season that it was time to speak up.</p>
        <p>''He gets mauled every game,'' Shanahan said. ''Mats Sundin goes down, first shift of the first period, penalty. Jaromir Jagr has to carry guys on his back all season long. I don't know what it is, if there's some sort of prejudice against him or what it is.</p>
        <p>''Guys hit him late. Guys hit him high. Guys hook his hands. The referees just seem to have a different set of rules for the way people get to play against him.''</p>
        <p>For much of the Rangers' frustrating season, they have relied almost exclusively on Jagr's line for their scoring. During games like last night's, when Jagr's line is shut down, the Rangers struggle to score. Their goal came on a power play, a shot by Jagr that ricocheted off Shanahan's skate in the second period.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers had only two power plays to Toronto's six, and the frustration over that statistic prompted Shanahan to raise his voice in complaint. At 38, as one of the league's elder statesmen and most respected players. He knows he has a stage, and he decided it was time to use it.</p>
        <p>''The N.B.A. didn't let people grab Jordan by the waist every time he went up for a jump shot,'' Shanahan said. ''Jags has had to play through that all season long. I've seen it. I've been amazed by it all year.''</p>
        <p>Shanahan said he had not seen referees look the other way so much since Slava Fetisov was one of the first players to come from the Soviet Union to play in the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>Rangers Coach Tom Renney was surprised a bit by Shanahan's speech, but he agreed. ''It makes you wonder,'' Renney said.</p>
        <p>Jagr did not take up his own cause, but he did take issue with the officiating.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, they had more power plays,'' Jagr said. ''I don't know how that happened. Wow. Sometimes you just have to close your eyes.''</p>
        <p>Even so, the Rangers did play this game closely, and it was decided by a breakaway goal by Sundin in the third period. Toronto goalie Andrew Raycroft may have been as responsible as anyone for the Rangers' foul mood, making 37 saves and surviving a barrage by the Rangers in the third period.</p>
        <p>''It was a real physical game, but you have to find a way to win these games,'' Toronto Coach Paul Maurice said. ''You can't do it without your goalie.''</p>
        <p>Each team scored a power-play goal in the second period, both of which bounced off a skate. After Shanahan's goal, at 12 minutes 7 seconds, the Maple Leafs got theirs nearly a minute and a half later, when a shot by Alexei Ponikarovsky bounced off Rangers defenseman Aaron Ward and past Henrik Lundqvist.</p>
        <p>''It was a series of bad bounces,'' Ward said. ''I knew I was in trouble when the puck went down low and I was standing in no-man's land between three guys. It happens.''</p>
        <p>Sundin scored the winning goal with 13:28 left, when a shot by Rangers defenseman Karel Rachunek was intercepted by Toronto defenseman Ian White, who spotted Sundin charging ahead of everyone toward the Rangers' goal.</p>
        <p>The teams were jockeying for position in the playoff race, and the victory pushed Toronto (25-21-6) 2 points ahead of the Rangers, and into a tie with Tampa Bay and Pittsburgh for seventh place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The Rangers not only fell to 25-22-4, they also fell below .500 at home (10-11-3). That is a source of frustration as big as the referees' suspected treatment of Jagr.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed with the home record, absolutely,'' Renney said. ''These fans are so good. We have to get winning in front of them because they can help feed us, give us the type of energy we need to push forward. But if we play like this, we'll win here.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Rangers defenseman Michal Rozsival missed the game with what the team described as a mildly sprained ligament in his knee.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
