<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ewing Jr. Follows Dad's Path to Garden</title>
    <meta content="01ewing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01ewing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georgetown University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Georgetown University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ewing, Patrick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DA153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ewing Jr. Follows Dad's Path to Garden</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Patrick Ewing Jr. Follows Dad's Path</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patrick Ewing Jr, son of former NBA player Patrick Ewing, plays for father's alma mater Georgetown University; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Home games are fine, said Patrick Ewing Jr., who plays basketball for Georgetown under the coaching of John Thompson III. But Ewing said he preferred road games, especially when spectators speak.</p>
        <p>''Fans will say things like, 'Your daddy's better,' '' he said late last week. ''They think I don't know that already? I like to shut people up. I'm more focused on proving to them that I'm not my father. I'm myself. I can do my own thing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Ewing Jr.’s next road game will have special significance when the Georgetown Hoyas play St. John’s on Thursday night at Madison Square Garden, where Ewing’s father starred from 1985 through 2000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Home games are fine, said Patrick Ewing Jr., who plays basketball for Georgetown under the coaching of John Thompson III. But Ewing said he preferred road games, especially when spectators speak.</p>
        <p>''Fans will say things like, 'Your daddy's better,' '' he said late last week. ''They think I don't know that already? I like to shut people up. I'm more focused on proving to them that I'm not my father. I'm myself. I can do my own thing.''</p>
        <p>His next road game will have special significance. The Hoyas (15-5, 5-2 Big East) will play St. John's (12-9, 3-5) on Thursday night at Madison Square Garden, where Ewing's father starred with the Knicks from 1985 through 2000.</p>
        <p>Although Ewing took a few practice shots at the Garden when his father was in the National Basketball Association, this will be his first competition in an arena populated by opinionated fans who consider themselves aficionados.</p>
        <p>''Right now, I'm more excited than anything,'' Ewing said. ''I finally get to suit up and play at the Garden. You look up at the rafters and you see all the retired jerseys there and you just think, 'Wow.' Every person that likes basketball should love Madison Square Garden.''</p>
        <p>More than two decades ago, his father, Patrick Ewing, was the star player for Georgetown. Thompson's father, John Thompson Jr., was the team's celebrated coach. They helped the Hoyas reach the N.C.A.A. championship game three times, winning the title in 1984.</p>
        <p>Now, the younger Thompson is in his third season as the Hoyas' coach. When he heard that Ewing would leave Indiana after his sophomore year in 2004-5, he persuaded him to transfer to Georgetown, although Ewing had to sit out a season before becoming eligible to play. Thompson had known him since Ewing was in diapers.</p>
        <p>''Coach Thompson was the first person to call me up,'' said Ewing, who was hesitant at first because of his father's legacy. ''I didn't want to put that on myself,'' he said. But Thompson persuaded him that neither of them needed to be burdened by the fame of their fathers. ''He said, 'You're your own person and your own player,' '' Ewing said.</p>
        <p>Ewing's father was a 7-foot center who started and averaged 15.3 points a game in his college career. Ewing Jr. is a 6-8 junior forward who comes off the bench to add energy with plays that do not always translate into statistics.</p>
        <p>He showed that last week in victories over DePaul and Cincinnati here at the Verizon Center. In chasing a loose ball against the Bearcats, Ewing crashed into the Cincinnati bench. In both games he defended with intensity -- a hallmark of his father's game -- to help his team increase leads.</p>
        <p>He also showed shooting range by sinking two 3-point attempts on Saturday against Cincinnati. He played a combined 29 minutes in the past two games and now averages more than 10 minutes a game. He is contributing 3.4 points and 1.6 rebounds a game.</p>
        <p>In his breakthrough game, a loss at Pittsburgh earlier this season, Ewing played 22 minutes and scored 12 points. Against DePaul and Cincinnati, Ewing was a loud supporter of teammates from the bench, waving towels to celebrate successes, and rushing from his chair to pat backs during timeouts.</p>
        <p>Against DePaul, when leaping to cheer a Hoyas field goal, Ewing almost collided with Thompson, who also leaped from his chair before shoving Ewing with two hands toward the scorer's table for a substitution.</p>
        <p>''His work ethic and his enthusiasm are contagious,'' Thompson said. ''Even last year, when he was in street clothes, he helped us win games just with his energy. He's someone that I think one day could be a coach because of his understanding of what's going on.''</p>
        <p>One star of the team is Roy Hibbert, a 7-2 junior center who leads the team in scoring with 12.5 points and 6.2 rebounds a game. But immediately after Ewing entered Saturday's game in a second-half substitution, he motioned for Hibbert and his teammates to gather around him to plot strategy.</p>
        <p>While Ewing spoke in the huddle, Hibbert nodded his head. ''He's always telling me, 'Roy, you do this and this,' and I listen to him,' '' Hibbert said. ''He's my roommate.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Wallace, a junior guard, described Ewing as ''like a ghost'' because he appeared on the court suddenly and unexpectedly.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people don't really notice him that much, but we do,'' Wallace said. ''We notice the small things that he does. He's all over the floor, getting loose balls and rebounds.''</p>
        <p>Ewing spoke last week while sitting in a conference room at McDonough Arena, the team's practice gym. Behind him was a large photograph of his father in a gray Georgetown uniform. The picture was shot from behind his father's broad back, his arms extended, with No. 33 beneath his name.</p>
        <p>The elder Ewing was in the audience when his son was introduced at McDonough for the Midnight Madness event to kick off the season. Ewing Jr. emerged in the spotlight to the music of ''Stuntin' Like My Daddy.'' His shirt displayed the same No. 33.</p>
        <p>As the fans chanted ''Pat-rick! Pat-rick,'' the senior Ewing walked down to the floor, and the current players pushed the son toward his father. They hugged. ''I told him, like, 'I love you,' '' Ewing Jr. recalled. ''It felt good, being able to hug your dad in front of everybody.''</p>
        <p>He said his father never pressured him to play basketball and stressed education over sports. ''He probably would have rather me not play,'' Ewing Jr. said. ''But watching him play, I couldn't help but want to be just like him, good as he was.''</p>
        <p>When Patrick Ewing was finishing his N.B.A. career with Orlando in 2001-2, his son visited him on an off-day, and they played one-on-one, as they often had before.</p>
        <p>''I tried to get serious, and I ended up winning a game,'' Ewing Jr. said. That was a first. ''And we played another game after that,'' he added. ''I missed my first shot and never got the ball back. He beat me, 11-0. And then he told me, 'That will be the first and only time you will ever beat me.' And he won't play me any more.''</p>
        <p>Patrick Ewing confirmed the story Saturday at the Verizon Center, where he watched from a courtside seat. ''Yeah,'' he said, smiling. ''Once was enough.''</p>
        <p>Ewing Sr., 44, coached as an assistant with the Houston Rockets last season and said he was taking this season off to watch the basketball exploits of his son in college and his daughter at a New Jersey high school, but he added that he hoped to return to basketball next season in a coaching or administrative role.</p>
        <p>Regarding his son's play this season, he said: ''He's doing real good. I couldn't be any more proud of him.''</p>
        <p>Later, the intergenerational interaction continued when Thompson's father, John Jr., spotted the younger Ewing in a dress suit in the hallway outside the locker room. The elder Thompson put his arm around the younger Ewing, pulled him toward him and put his mouth near his ear.</p>
        <p>As he spoke softly and intently, slight smiles grew on both men's faces. Those standing nearby seemed to edge backward, away from them, in small steps. Although it was a crowded and public place, this chat seemed private, intimate and personal, like family.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
