<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agudio and Hofstra Top Virginia Commonwealth</title>
    <meta content="01hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01hoops.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hofstra University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Commonwealth University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hofstra University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDA153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agudio and Hofstra Top Virginia Commonwealth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Agudio and Hofstra Top Virginia Commonwealth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hofstra University defeats Virginia Commonwealth Univeristy, 79-68; other men's college basketball results noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Already playing with his left thumb wrapped and his left calf encased in an elastic sleeve, Hofstra guard Antoine Agudio came up limping late in a tight game Wednesday. He grimaced, tightened his shoelaces and stayed in the game.</p>
        <p>He then scored a fast-break basket, underscoring not only his grittiness, but also his value to the Pride, which handed Virginia Commonwealth its first conference loss, 79-68, in front of 3,752 at the Mack Sports Complex.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Injured Hofstra guard Antoine Agudio scored a fast-break basket within seconds, underscoring not only his grittiness, but also his value to the Pride, which handed Virginia Commonwealth its first conference loss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Already playing with his left thumb wrapped and his left calf encased in an elastic sleeve, Hofstra guard Antoine Agudio came up limping late in a tight game Wednesday. He grimaced, tightened his shoelaces and stayed in the game.</p>
        <p>He then scored a fast-break basket, underscoring not only his grittiness, but also his value to the Pride, which handed Virginia Commonwealth its first conference loss, 79-68, in front of 3,752 at the Mack Sports Complex.</p>
        <p>Agudio, a junior, led Hofstra (17-6, 10-2 Colonial Athletic Association) with 30 points, his season high. He made 10 of 17 shots from the floor, including four 3-pointers, in a game in which the Pride shot 50 percent.</p>
        <p>''I love being out there the whole time,'' said Agudio, who played all 40 minutes. ''This is what I live for. Regardless of what the score is, regardless of who we're playing, I love being out there.''</p>
        <p>Agudio said he twisted his right ankle while playing defense with less than two minutes left in the game. Before limping out of the interview room, Agudio said he did not expect the injury to be a problem.</p>
        <p>''If you don't have ice on your body at this time of year, then you're not playing hard enough,'' Hofstra Coach Tom Pecora said.</p>
        <p>Loren Stokes, who came into the game as Hofstra's leading scorer, added 21 points for the Pride, including a 3-point play and a layup off a steal in the last five minutes to end the Rams' 10-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>Hofstra needed superb efforts from its guards to beat V.C.U. (19-4, 11-1) -- a team that stretches its tentacles all over the floor on defense -- and Agudio, Stokes and Carlos Rivera played nearly flawlessly. The Pride had a season-low six turnovers.</p>
        <p>''We handled their pressure really well,'' Agudio said. ''We didn't force any bad shots, either.''</p>
        <p>Virginia Commonwealth, which had the No. 1 offense in the conference, shot only 40 percent from the floor. The Rams made 9 of 26 shots in the first half, enabling the Pride to build a lead it would keep.</p>
        <p>''They seemed like they were constantly a step ahead of everything we did tonight,'' V.C.U. Coach Anthony Grant said.</p>
        <p>Hofstra could have played Wednesday for a share of first place in the C.A.A., but Delaware, which is in last place, defeated the Pride on Monday. So V.C.U. brought a two-game lead into Wednesday's game.</p>
        <p>''We knew we slipped up in Delaware,'' Stokes said.</p>
        <p>Hofstra prevented V.C.U. from applying more pressure to dictate a faster tempo. After V.C.U.'s Jesse Pellot-Rosa made an off-balance 3-pointer to cut the deficit to 51-50 with 9 minutes 4 seconds to play, Mike Davis-Sabb beat the shot clock and hit a jumper.</p>
        <p>Hofstra kept at least a 3-point lead for the rest of the game.</p>
        <p>''We played to our potential tonight,'' Pecora said, ''and that's all you can ask for.''</p>
        <p>INDIANA 71, WISCONSIN 66 -- A. J. Ratliff scored 18 of his season-high 20 points in the second half and host Indiana (16-5, 6-2 Big Ten) defeated No. 2 Wisconsin (21-2, 7-1), ending its 17-game winning streak. (AP)</p>
        <p>FLORIDA 74, VANDERBILT 64 -- Lee Humphrey made three 3-pointers in a row to spark host Florida's rally from a double-digit deficit, and the No. 1 Gators (20-2, 7-0 Southeastern Conference) defeated No. 24 Vanderbilt (15-7, 5-3) for their 13th consecutive victory. (AP)</p>
        <p>NORTH CAROLINA 105, MIAMI 64 -- Tyler Hansbrough had 22 points and 13 rebounds to lead No. 3 North Carolina (20-2, 6-1 Atlantic Coast Conference) past visiting Miami (9-13, 2-6) for its fifth win in a row. (AP)</p>
        <p>OHIO STATE 78, PURDUE 60 -- Mike Conley scored 18 points to help No. 4 Ohio State (19-3, 7-1 Big Ten) defeat host Purdue (14-8, 3-5) for its sixth consecutive victory. (AP)</p>
        <p>BUTLER 71, YOUNGSTOWN ST. 58 -- Mike Green scored a season-high 23 points and No. 13 Butler (21-2, 9-1 Horizon League) won its seventh in a row, beating host Youngstown State (9-14, 4-7). (AP)</p>
        <p>WEST VIRGINIA 89, RUTGERS 83 -- Joe Alexander and Da'Sean Butler each scored 17 to lead West Virginia (17-4, 6-3 Big East) past host Rutgers (9-13, 2-7). Rutgers lost for the sixth time in seven games. (AP)</p>
        <p>FORDHAM 67, ST. BONAVENTURE 61 -- Sebastian Greene scored 18 points as host Fordham (13-7, 6-2 Atlantic 10) extended its winning streak to five with a victory against St. Bonaventure (6-15, 3-5). (AP)</p>
        <p>DEPAUL 66, CONNECTICUT 58 -- Draelon Burns scored a career-high 26 points and host DePaul (13-10, 4-5 Big East) defeated Connecticut (13-8, 2-6), which has lost five in a row. (AP)</p>
        <p>IN OTHER GAMES -- Ben McCauley scored 20 to lead host North Carolina State (12-8, 2-5 A.C.C.) past No. 16 Virginia Tech (16-6, 6-2), 70-59.  Jermareo Davidson had a career-high 31 points and No. 19 Alabama (16-5, 3-4 SEC) defeated host Louisiana State (13-8, 2-5), 73-70. Kevin Durant had 37 points and a season-high 23 rebounds to lead No. 22 Texas (16-5, 6-1 Big 12) past host Texas Tech (15-7, 4-3), 76-64. (AP)</p>
        <p>WOMEN</p>
        <p>TEXAS 67, OKLAHOMA 62 -- Tiffany Jackson had 22 points and 13 rebounds, and host Texas (15-7, 4-4) sent No. 9 Oklahoma (17-3, 7-2) to its second loss in a row after 26 consecutive Big 12 wins. (AP)</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
