<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases; The Apartment Was Mostly Empty, Except for the Love</title>
    <meta content="01neediest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Children's Aid Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Potts, Monica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DB153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases; The Apartment Was Mostly Empty, Except for the Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONICA POTTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Potts, Monica</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Children's Aid Society, one of seven beneficiaries of New York Times Neediest Cases Fund, helps woman find job and move into new apartment in Bronx; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new apartment in the Bronx that Lorraine Robinson shares with her 12-year-old cousin, Tyrik Sherman, was mostly empty in January, two months after they moved in. They kept plastic patio chairs in the kitchen, a substitute for more permanent furniture. A plastic storage bin became a table.</p>
        <p>But though the setting felt sparse to them, it also felt like home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The new apartment in the Bronx that Lorraine Robinson shares with her 12-year-old cousin, Tyrik Sherman, was mostly empty in January, two months after they moved in. They kept plastic patio chairs in the kitchen, a substitute for more permanent furniture. A plastic storage bin became a table.</p>
        <p>But though the setting felt sparse to them, it also felt like home.</p>
        <p>Even before Tyrik lived with her, Ms. Robinson, 26, had plenty to do. In the spring of 2005, she had a full-time job as a receptionist at a nursing home and was taking accounting classes at Monroe College in the Bronx. She also spent two or three days a week with her mother, Laura, who had bone cancer.</p>
        <p>But if her life was already a busy one, a phone call from her mother that April made it a lot busier.</p>
        <p>''She called me one day at work and said, 'I need you to take custody of Tyrik,' '' Ms. Robinson recalled.</p>
        <p>As Laura Robinson became sicker, she was less able to take care of Tyrik, Laura's sister's son, whom Laura adopted when he was a baby.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinson has two older sisters, but they have children of their own. Mostly, though, she thinks that her mother believed that Tyrik's lot in life would be better with her, and that she would provide him with a sense of ambition. ''She really thought I was the best one to take care of him,'' Ms. Robinson said.</p>
        <p>When Laura Robinson's condition worsened, Tyrik stayed with his mother and stepfather, and Ms. Robinson visited him to make sure he was getting his homework done and had everything he needed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinson missed many days of work because of her mother's illness, and her obligations were becoming harder to balance. Tyrik, who is on medication for attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and other medical conditions, began having problems in school.</p>
        <p>Caring for him and managing the paperwork to become his legal guardian and continue his Medicaid was also hard. Ms. Robinson lost her job in August 2005.</p>
        <p>Then, in September 2005, a month before Laura Robinson died at 50, Tyrik moved into Ms. Robinson's studio apartment. He slept on a futon. Savings and unemployment tided them over for a while. Ms. Robinson also had student loans, and borrowed more money as a living subsidy.</p>
        <p>After about a year, though, the money had run out, and she did not want to borrow more on her student loans. She had to apply for welfare, breaking a lifetime vow to never rely on public assistance.</p>
        <p>''It was either that or put him in foster care,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Last fall, however, Ms. Robinson found help when she needed it most. A counselor at Tyrik's school told her about the Children's Aid Society, one of seven beneficiaries of The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund. The agency has been helping her find a job and, when she found a two-bedroom apartment in the East Tremont section of the Bronx, Children's Aid helped her move in.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinson had to pay more than $3,000 in deposits and broker fees before she could move in.</p>
        <p>She is enrolled in Section 8, and the city's Human Resources Department covered most of the fees, but she was short $556. Children's Aid drew on the Neediest Cases for the money, as well as $200 for clothes for Tyrik.</p>
        <p>Her caseworker, Unique Morris, has applied to the Neediest Cases for more money to furnish the apartment.</p>
        <p>Moving Ms. Robinson and Tyrik out of the studio was a priority for Mr. Morris. He felt that the crowded studio was hampering their relationship.</p>
        <p>''It seems like this apartment is bringing them together as a family,'' Mr. Morris said.</p>
        <p>Though her life has been hectic, Ms. Robinson managed to earn an associate's degree in accounting in August. She plans to get her bachelor's degree this December, then become a certified public accountant. Until then, she and Mr. Morris are looking for a job that will allow her to get off public assistance and bolster her résumé.</p>
        <p>For now, there is table-top air hockey to play. Tyrik, who is energetic and speaks so quickly he can be hard to understand, received the game as a gift from his stepfather. Conversation during the game between Tyrik and Ms. Robinson centered mostly on who might be cheating, and who was really winning.</p>
        <p>''I'm a sore loser,'' Ms. Robinson admitted, laughing.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded: $7,444,241.71  Recorded Tuesday: 3,837.41  Total: $7,448,079.12  Last year to date: $6,703,267.70</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to 4 Chase Metrotech Center, 7th Floor East, Lockbox 5193, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11245, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street  Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street  Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue  New York, N.Y. 10022</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22nd Street  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22nd Street  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station  P.O. Box 4100  New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card by phone at (800) 381-0075 or online, courtesy of NYCharities.org, an Internet donations service, at www.nytimes.com/neediest or www.nycharities.org/neediest. For instructions on how to donate stock to the fund, call (212) 556-1137 or fax (212) 556-4450.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
