<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home After 5 Road Games, Nets Still Have Miles to Go</title>
    <meta content="01nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/01/sports/basketball/01nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eligon, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McDyess, Antonio</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EEDA153FF932A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home After 5 Road Games, Nets Still Have Miles to Go</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Home After 5 Road Games, Nets Still Have Miles to Go</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Detroit Pistons defeat New Jersey Nets, 113-89; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Detroit Pistons' Jason Maxiell missed a jump shot midway through the second quarter, but a teammate, Antonio McDyess, kept the play alive by tapping the ball back out to Maxiell. McDyess then missed a jump shot, but another teammate, Carlos Delfino, corralled the rebound.</p>
        <p>The Pistons finally ended the possession with a 13-footer by McDyess that extended their lead to 13 points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After making several strides in the right direction  like showing that they had a formidable bench and that Vince Carter was a superstar  the Nets belly-flopped in their first home game in a week and a half.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Detroit Pistons' Jason Maxiell missed a jump shot midway through the second quarter, but a teammate, Antonio McDyess, kept the play alive by tapping the ball back out to Maxiell. McDyess then missed a jump shot, but another teammate, Carlos Delfino, corralled the rebound.</p>
        <p>The Pistons finally ended the possession with a 13-footer by McDyess that extended their lead to 13 points.</p>
        <p>That was just one example of the impact that five mentally and physically trying games thousands of miles from home had on the Nets on Wednesday night at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The most damaging evidence was the final score: Pistons 113, Nets 89.</p>
        <p>After making several strides in the right direction behind the play of Vince Carter and their formidable bench, the Nets (22-24) belly-flopped in their first home game in a week and a half.</p>
        <p>Granted, they may have been tired after arriving back in New Jersey early Tuesday morning. But against one of the top teams in the Eastern Conference, this was not the performance the Nets wanted.</p>
        <p>Their struggles were embodied in Carter, who had appeared unstoppable in the Nets' previous three games, averaging 35.3 points and shooting 66.1 percent from the field. But against the Pistons, he reverted to the inconsistency for which he is often criticized.</p>
        <p>He missed his first eight shots and did not have a field goal until a dunk with 7 minutes 44 seconds to play in the third quarter. He finished with 11 points and made only 4 of 15 field-goal attempts.</p>
        <p>Detroit Coach Flip Saunders said that the Pistons changed their defensive schemes against Carter from the last time these teams played and tried to trap him at halfcourt.</p>
        <p>''We got them frustrated,'' Saunders said.</p>
        <p>Carter said: ''It's just one of those nights. You got to swallow it and move on.''</p>
        <p>Reviewing the game film probably will not do much good for the Nets' digestive tracts.</p>
        <p>The Pistons had their way on offense, shooting 54.4 percent from the field. They also proved to be the aggressors, making a whopping 33 of 38 free-throw attempts.</p>
        <p>''As a team, we just didn't play well,'' said Jason Kidd, who scored 15 points but had only 2 assists. ''They got anything they wanted.''</p>
        <p>In the opening minutes, the Nets appeared ready, especially center Mikki Moore. He scored 18 points in the first quarter and shot 8 of 10 from the field. Entering this season, 18 points was Moore's career high. But he scored only 2 points the rest of the game for a team-high 20.</p>
        <p>''They changed their defensive scheme,'' Moore said. ''They were sitting there waiting on me the whole time.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Every team has a rough game when they come off a long road trip like this.''</p>
        <p>The Pistons began pulling away early in the second quarter with a 15-6 run that gave them a 12-point advantage with 7:30 remaining.</p>
        <p>The Pistons just about sucked the last bit of fight out the Nets by outscoring them by 13-4 over the first five minutes of the second quarter. The Nets missed four of five field-goal attempts during that stretch.</p>
        <p>The reserves for the All-Star Game are scheduled to be announced Thursday, and four of the top candidates for the Eastern Conference's two backcourt spots were on the court here: Kidd and Carter, and Chauncey Billups and Richard Hamilton of the Pistons.</p>
        <p>Hamilton (24 points) and Billups (18 points) certainly proved they were worthy of playing in the All-Star game. But the Nets' guards may have a better shot of making it.</p>
        <p>Carter missed making the starting lineup by 3,010 votes, the slimmest margin in 17 years. That was in the fan voting, however, and the head coaches select the reserves.</p>
        <p>Saunders said he voted for Kidd.</p>
        <p>''I'd be shocked if he didn't make it,'' Saunders said before Wednesday's game. ''Guys that have been great players in this league, as they get older, their games evolve and they find ways to change and still make themselves more effective.</p>
        <p>''In some ways he's more effective now than he was when he was quicker.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Nets forward Richard Jefferson spoke with reporters about his arthroscopic ankle surgery for the first time, but he did not provide many details. Jefferson, who was on crutches and wearing a medical boot, said he was not sure when he would begin rehabilitation or when he would return to the court. (Estimates have been six weeks.) He seemed certain about one thing: he would not rush back from the injury. ''There's no need in coming back early and hurting yourself and missing more time,'' he said.  Marcus Williams, the Nets' rookie point guard, was selected to play in the rookie-sophomore game during the All-Star Game weekend.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
