<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oilmen Meet With Cubans in Mexico, but U.S. Intervenes</title>
    <meta content="04cuba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico City (Mexico)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sheraton Maria Isabel Hotel (Mexico City)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starwood Hotels &amp; Resorts Worldwide Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Office of Foreign Assets Control</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Mexico City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD8163EF937A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oilmen Meet With Cubans in Mexico, but U.S. Intervenes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Feb. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Delegation of Cubans, meeting with American oil executives, leaves Sheraton Maria Isabel Hotel in Mexico City following request to hotel's American owner, Starwood Hotels, from Treasury Department's Office of Foreign Assets Control; American law prohibits hotel from supplying services to Cuban individuals or companies; action is latest in what seems to be hardening by Bush administration of trade embargo against Cuba; Cuban officials are trying to court American petroleum companies to produce oil in territorial waters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>United States government officials said Friday that they had asked the owner of a hotel here, which is part of an American corporation, to expel a Cuban delegation that was meeting with American oil executives.</p>
        <p>The delegation later left the hotel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>United States government officials said Friday that they had asked the owner of a hotel here, which is part of an American corporation, to expel a Cuban delegation that was meeting with American oil executives.</p>
        <p>The delegation later left the hotel.</p>
        <p>The request was made by the Treasury Department's Office of Foreign Assets Control, which told Starwood Hotels, the owner of the Sheraton Maria Isabel in Mexico City, that American law prohibited it from supplying services to Cuban individuals or companies. The move is the latest in what seems be a hardening by the Bush administration of the trade embargo against Cuba.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Treasury Department, Molly Millerwise, said, ''The hotel acted in accordance with U.S. sanctions.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Starwood Hotels, Nadeen Ayala, confirmed that the Treasury Department had asked the hotel ''to have the Cuban nationals leave.''</p>
        <p>Cuban officials are trying to court American petroleum companies to produce oil in the nation's territorial waters after succeeding in attracting exploratory investments from Chinese, Indian and Norwegian energy companies. The meeting of largely Texan oil executives and elite bureaucrats from Havana began Thursday and was to end Saturday.</p>
        <p>''It's outrageous that I, as an American citizen, can't go and talk to someone on Mexican soil,'' said Kirby Jones, a former World Bank official and the organizer of the meeting for the U.S.-Cuba Trade Association, a nonprofit group in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones said this was the 10th meeting he had organized between American executives and Cuban officials, although it was the first to focus on opportunities for American energy companies in Cuba.</p>
        <p>Previous meetings had resulted in sales of American food products to Cuba.</p>
        <p>This week's meeting, Mr. Jones said, was originally scheduled for December in Cancún, Mexico, but was rescheduled for Mexico City.</p>
        <p>Other meetings had been at hotels controlled by American companies, he said, including a hotel in Cancún, where the energy meeting was originally scheduled in December.</p>
        <p>''This issue has never come up,'' Mr. Jones said. The American executives will try to meet with the Cubans at another location on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Some of the largest American oil companies, including Exxon Mobil and the Valero Energy Corporation, had agreed to meet with Cuban officials on what was thought to be neutral ground at a hotel here in the cradle of Mexican capitalism, a short stroll on Paseo de la Reforma from a Starbucks, the United States Embassy and Mexico's stock exchange. The oil-importing Port of Corpus Christi and American shipping and oil field equipment companies also sent representatives.</p>
        <p>''They're sensing a lost opportunity in their own backyard, less than 100 miles from the Florida coast,'' said Mr. Jones.</p>
        <p>Although Cuba has suffered from energy shortages since the Soviet Union halted subsidized oil shipments more than a decade ago, its potential as an oil producer has caught attention.</p>
        <p>According to the Energy Information Administration, Cuba's proven oil reserves of 750 million barrels exceed those of Sudan, an African nation that has lured large non-American investments to its oil industry despite American economic sanctions in place since 1997.</p>
        <p>''We have absolutely no limitations on working with American oil companies. The barriers, unfortunately, come from the other side,'' said Alberto Wong Calvo, director of hydrocarbons at the National Office of Mineral Resources in Cuba.</p>
        <p>Oil production in Cuba has surged since an opening to foreign investment in the 1990's, with operations by two Canadian companies, the Sherritt International Corporation and Pebercan Inc., helping to increase output to about 70,000 barrels a day in 2005 from a low of 18,000 barrels a day in 1992. Cuba consumes more than 150,000 barrels a day, with Venezuela providing imports on favorable financial terms.</p>
        <p>The American economic embargo on dealings with Cuba prohibits energy companies from reaching exploration deals with Unión Cubapetróleo, Cuba's national oil company. But executives who attended the conference said they were encouraged by the recent relaxation of restrictions on American food exports to Cuba and the implications of Chinese rigs searching for oil this year in Cuban waters off the Straits of Florida.</p>
        <p>''It's a difficult road ahead, but we're in the same neighborhood,'' said Amado Durón, director of operations at Valero Energy, the San Antonio-based refining company that could profit from processing Cuban oil at its refineries in Texas, Louisiana or the island of Aruba.</p>
        <p>Cuba has been busy reaching exploration deals in the last year with Sinopec, the energy concern controlled by the Chinese government, ONGC Videsh of India and Norsk Hydro of Norway. So far, however, none of the ventures have found large fields like those in the American waters of the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Repsol of Spain spent $20 million on drilling that came tantalizingly close to a commercial discovery, but executives said oil from the field only partly met expectations. Petrobras of Brazil shelved Cuban exploration efforts after hitting a dry hole in 2001. Still, elevated oil prices have brought frontier plays like Cuba into play.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
