<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vacation Packages: Comparing Choices</title>
    <meta content="15prac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1732431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER: BOOKING ON THE WEB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D81F30F936A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vacation Packages: Comparing Choices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S little surprise that vacation packages are the hottest sellers for online agencies like Expedia, Orbitz and Travelocity. By booking flights and hotels together, after all, travelers can save themselves both some clicks and cash.</p>
        <p>But now technology is making it easier for individual airlines and hotels to sell packages themselves on the Internet, offering consumers a wider array of choices than in years past and presenting still more evidence of the escalating online competition between travel companies and agents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S little surprise that vacation packages are the hottest sellers for online agencies like Expedia, Orbitz and Travelocity. By booking flights and hotels together, after all, travelers can save themselves both some clicks and cash.</p>
        <p>But now technology is making it easier for individual airlines and hotels to sell packages themselves on the Internet, offering consumers a wider array of choices than in years past and presenting still more evidence of the escalating online competition between travel companies and agents.</p>
        <p>In recent months, JetBlue.com rolled out its first vacation package service, Marriott.com upgraded its vacations, and American Airlines added last-minute vacations to its mix of packages. Since airline sites will offer no choice in carriers, and hotel sites will likewise exclude all but their own properties, many travelers may think twice before approaching these sites when online agencies offer much more choice.</p>
        <p>For many reasons, though, it's worth the effort. Start with the obvious: travelers who favor a particular hotel or airline will want to check its Web site, either out of allegiance or to fatten their loyalty accounts.</p>
        <p>JetBlue fans, for instance, could literally find nothing in the way of packages until November, when the company started JetBlue Getaways on its site. (The vacations are also available via a toll-free number, 800-538-2583.)</p>
        <p>The company chose not to rely on wholesalers or other travel agents to team its airplane seats with hoteliers because it wanted to build direct relationships with hotels, said Rusty McNeal, JetBlue's director of vacation planning. Mr. McNeal said the company expected to be able to offer better deals with hotels throughout the year because JetBlue had committed itself to these properties, ''rather than just coming in during the high season and forgetting about promotions in the low season or certain times of the week.''</p>
        <p>One example of how such a direct relationship can bear fruit, Mr. McNeal said, is in how JetBlue.com is marketing the Monte Carlo Resort and Casino in Las Vegas, a four-star property. In December, the site was offering round-trip air fare from J.F.K. to Las Vegas and two weekend nights at the hotel for $365 a person. (Weekend hotel rates range from $100 to $400 a night.)</p>
        <p>''We're not always promoting the lowest-price hotel, which also makes us a little different from others,'' Mr. McNeal said. ''Most of ours are four- and five-star hotels, '' which, he added, are properties more in line with the tastes of his company's customers.</p>
        <p>Others on the site include the Luxor in Las Vegas and the British Colonial Hilton in Nassau.</p>
        <p>Indeed, other packages offered online typically feature hotels with lesser ratings to cater to those who might be traveling on a tighter budget. For example, United.com featured the Homestead Studios Suites, a one-star hotel in Salt Lake City, while Travelocity featured the Day's Inn in Springville, Utah, near Provo.</p>
        <p>Members of the TrueBlue loyalty program of JetBlue can also earn points if they book the vacation on the company's Web site, just as members of loyalty programs at Northwest, American and Marriott do when they book packages on those companies' sites.</p>
        <p>Henry H. Harteveldt, a travel analyst with Forrester Research, said, ''Airlines and hotels want to do as little vacation business as possible through online travel agencies because of the costs involved, and also customer control.''</p>
        <p>When customers book through agency sites, not only must airlines and hotels pay a commission, but consumers can also easily stray to other airlines and hotels, even if they had an allegiance to a particular company. Not only can travel companies avoid paying agency fees by selling vacations directly to consumers, Mr. Harteveldt said, but they can also establish relationships with their customers and keep them coming back to their sites.</p>
        <p>For these reasons, hotels and airlines have become more aggressive in recent years about attracting customers directly to their sites. In the last year in particular, hotels and airlines have pushed harder to attract customers with many hotels guaranteeing that no other sites will sell their rooms for less.</p>
        <p>Of course, that customer-company loyalty goes only so far. While airline and hotel companies are often happy to award points for vacation bookings on their own Web sites, they generally stop short of allowing members of their loyalty programs to pay for the vacations with points.</p>
        <p>American Airlines is one exception. Recently, it offered a seven-night stay for two in late January at the Cliff Lodge and Spa in Snowbird, Utah, for $2,632, including round-trip air fare from New York to Salt Lake City. The price for the lodging alone on Snowbird.com, the resort's Web site, would have been $2,330, while the price for the flight on American's Web site would have been $577. The total saving with the package was $275.</p>
        <p>Moreover, American's AAdvantage members could spend 257,000 points on the vacation and knock the price down to $576. (Those who book through American's Last Minute Packages section cannot pay with points.)</p>
        <p>Analysts and industry executives say customers have a wider range of options than they did in years past, when airlines and hotels were more likely to offer a more static selection of vacation deals. With the advent of more sophisticated booking technology, airlines and hotels can plug into a deep inventory of seats and rooms to create packages dynamically.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, though, the biggest online agencies often sell that service to airlines and hotels. Take Cendant, which owns Orbitz and CheapTickets.com, among other companies. Cendant's Neat Group creates packages for the sites of SpiritAir, Marriott, Frontier and half of United's vacation package products (its Escapes brand).</p>
        <p>That can have significant implications for travelers. Mitch Truwit, chief executive of Cendant's Orbitz and CheapTickets divisions, said that while all the company's competitors ''have solid offerings'' in packages, Cendant has sought to build a stronger international inventory of hotel rooms. As a result, hotels that rely on Cendant's Neat Group to create packages for their sites could miss some bargains that Orbitz would offer, simply because the hotel site would present only its own properties.</p>
        <p>For instance, for a vacation to Salt Lake City, Orbitz offered a package including air fare and a stay at the Holiday Inn Express for $992, while Marriott's best deal was $1,145, with a room at the Courtyard by Marriott in Salt Lake City.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Harteveldt of Forrester said: ''This isn't as easy as buying an airline ticket from Point A to Point B. There could be subtle factors involved, such as the category of hotel room you're getting in the package. The hard thing about this is, you have to look beyond the price to really understand what you're getting.''</p>
        <p>CLICKING TO FIND SAVINGS ON A UTAH SKI VACATION  One ski vacation for two, please, from New York City to Salt Lake City from Jan. 22 to 29, with round-trip air fare and hotel.</p>
        <p>American Airlines (AA.com)</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare and seven nights at the Cliff Lodge and Spa in Snowbird, Utah, for $2,632. Saving off the flight and hotel booked separately: $275.</p>
        <p>Pros: Convenient location and flights.</p>
        <p>Cons: Flights depart from and arrive at different New York airports. Also, American's Web site often forces users into wasted clicks.</p>
        <p>JetBlue (JetBlue.com)</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare and seven nights at the Cliff Lodge and Spa for $2,610. Saving off flight and hotel booked separately: $190.</p>
        <p>Pros: Convenient hotel location, easy Web site experience.</p>
        <p>Cons: The return flight was a red-eye.</p>
        <p>United Airlines Escapes (United.com)</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare and seven nights at La Quinta Inn in Salt Lake City for $898. Saving off flight and hotel booked separately: $310.</p>
        <p>Pros: Easy Web site navigation, low price.</p>
        <p>Cons: The hotels listed were farther from ski areas than those in other packages.</p>
        <p>United Airlines Vacations (United.com)</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare and seven nights at the Homestead Studios Suites in Salt Lake City, for $845. Saving off flight and hotel booked separately: $204.</p>
        <p>Pros: Low price.</p>
        <p>Cons: One-star hotel. United Vacations offers a less user-friendly online experience than United Escapes.</p>
        <p>Marriott (Marriott.com)</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare on Northwest and seven nights at the Courtyard by Marriott Salt Lake City Airport, for $1,145. Saving off flight and room booked separately: $121.</p>
        <p>Pros: Good price at midtier hotel.</p>
        <p>Cons: Frustrating search system on the Web site.</p>
        <p>Starwood (SPGVacations.com)</p>
        <p>Deal: There were no packages in Salt Lake City, even though the site allows you to book flights separately to more than 60 airports and Starwood.com showed vacancies for the dates sought (at Sheraton City Center Hotel).</p>
        <p>Travelocity.com</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare on Delta and seven nights at a Days Inn in Springville, Utah, for $821. Saving off flight and room booked on suppliers' sites: $20.</p>
        <p>Pros: Inexpensive trip.</p>
        <p>Cons: Lower-tier hotel away from ski resorts and Salt Lake City.</p>
        <p>Expedia.com</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare on Northwest and seven nights at Red Lion Hotel Salt Lake Downtown for $1,324. Savings off flight and room booked on suppliers' sites: $72. (If booked separately on Expedia.com, $102.)</p>
        <p>Pros: Good midtier hotel.</p>
        <p>Cons: Little saved off à la carte price. Vacation package customers are not informed until later in the purchase process whether their purchase will result in frequent flier miles.</p>
        <p>Orbitz.com</p>
        <p>Deal: Air fare on Delta and seven nights at the Holiday Inn Express Salt Lake City for $992. Savings off flight and room booked on suppliers' sites: $39.</p>
        <p>Pros: Good location.</p>
        <p>Cons: Little in savings.</p>
        <p>BOB TEDESCHI</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER: BOOKING ON THE WEB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
