<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talk Network Makes Debut, With Rage A No-Show</title>
    <meta content="Y01RAD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/01/national/01RADI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040403T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1570767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Critic's Notebook"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air America Radio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franken, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Franken, Al</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Garofalo, Janeane</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0D91439F932A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talk Network Makes Debut, With Rage A No-Show</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Talk Network Makes Debut, With Rage a No-Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critic's Notebook finds debut of Air America, liberal radio network featuring comedian Al Franken, oddly subdued, offering little rage and ferocity that fuel right-wing radio (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tone of Air America was supposed to be as bold and belligerent as Rush Limbaugh or Sean Hannity, an unapologetically liberal riposte to the conservative radio talk shows that dominate the airwaves.</p>
        <p>The comedian Al Franken even named his three-hour program the ''The O'Franken Report,'' to tweak his conservative nemesis, Bill O'Reilly, yet his maiden show proved to be oddly subdued and, at times, defensive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rage  unbound by reason or reticence  is what fuels the most successful political talk shows, but there wasnt much of it on Air America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tone of Air America was supposed to be as bold and belligerent as Rush Limbaugh or Sean Hannity, an unapologetically liberal riposte to the conservative radio talk shows that dominate the airwaves.</p>
        <p>The comedian Al Franken even named his three-hour program the ''The O'Franken Report,'' to tweak his conservative nemesis, Bill O'Reilly, yet his maiden show proved to be oddly subdued and, at times, defensive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franken interviewed the salt-of-the-earth parents of his best friend in Minnesota to prove that liberals do not hate America, as the conservative commentator Ann Coulter has charged.</p>
        <p>''That's unbelievable,'' Carol Griffin, 77, said of the accusation while on vacation in Florida. ''Liberals are the ones that love America. Honestly.''</p>
        <p>There is little chance that Air America will overtake its conservative competitors any time soon. Rush Limbaugh is heard on more than 600 stations, including WABC in New York.</p>
        <p>The Air America Radio network made its debut in five markets: New York; Chicago; Los Angeles; Portland, Ore.; and San Bernardino-Riverside, Calif.</p>
        <p>Air America may yet grow as a radio network, but the first day mostly highlighted the difficulty of trying to match the fervor and ferocity of right-wing radio. Satire and sarcasm come more easily than rage to Mr. Franken, a former ''Saturday Night Live'' performer and writer. And rage -- unbound by reason or reticence -- is what fuels the most successful political talk shows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franken began his show by saying, ''Yeah, we are angry,'' but he never let loose with the kind of colorful, free-flowing rant that has proved so cathartic to like-minded listeners. (That sort of diatribe was provided later in the afternoon by the longtime liberal radio talk show host Randi Rhodes, who likened the Bushes to the Corleone family in ''The Godfather'' and said the president was Fredo.) Mr. Franken stuck instead to a middle ground of mockery and mild indignation.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration's handling or mishandling of the war on terror after the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks was the main topic on all the shows on Air America, which began at noon with Mr. Franken's show and ended with ''Majority Report, '' with the actress Janeane Garofalo and Sam Seder as hosts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franken's guests included Bob Kerrey, the former Democratic senator from Nebraska who is now a member of the Sept. 11 commission, the documentary filmmaker Michael Moore and, as a caller from Tennessee, former Vice President Al Gore. (''Hi, Al,'' Mr. Franken said. ''Hi, Al,'' Mr Gore replied.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's call was one of the show's highlights. Mr. Moore, who supported Ralph Nader in the 2000 election, had a few words to say to the Democratic nominee who won the popular vote but still lost the election to George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''We're really sorry, Al,'' Mr. Moore mumbled. Mr. Gore paused for a beat, then asked, ''For what, Michael?'' Mr. Moore then began a long, winding explanation of how he himself had not campaigned for Mr. Nader in swing states. Mr. Gore again paused, then added politely, ''What are you saying?''</p>
        <p>For the kickoff, Mr. Franken invited some of his more famous friends to make call-in cameos; Ben Stein, a former speechwriter for President Richard M. Nixon, was one. The other was G. Gordon Liddy of Watergate fame. They did not bring great material with them.</p>
        <p>Neither did Bob Elliott, who was the Bob of the old ''Bob &amp; Ray Show,'' and was tapped by Mr. Franken to perform a skit about a terrorist sneaking weapons onto an airplane. In the skit, a would-be hijacker-terrorist explains that he made his dog swallow a box-cutter before takeoff, saying, ''He gets airsick, or so we hope.''</p>
        <p>The national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, referred to as Condi, came under attack, as did Mr. Bush, Vice President Dick Cheney and Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld (Mr. Franken does a very funny impersonation of Mr. Rumsfeld). But most of Mr. Franken's ire was directed at conservative commentators, including Mr. Limbaugh and his drug problems and the outrageous statements of Ms. Coulter, whom Mr. Franken described as a ''walking horror show.'' On the show, Mr. Franken pretended to lock an irate Ms. Coulter, impersonated by the actress Bebe Neuwirth, in the green room.</p>
        <p>And clearly, it is conservative talk radio that galls Mr. Franken the most. ''The radical right wing has taken over the White House, Congress, and increasingly, the courts,'' he complained in his introductory remarks. ''And most insidiously, the airwaves.''</p>
        <p>Critic's Notebook  Correction:  April 3, 2004, Saturday  A Critic's Notebook article on Thursday about the premiere of the liberal radio network Air America omitted the stations on which its programs are heard. They are WLIB-AM (1190) in New York, WNTD-AM (950) in Chicago, KBLA-AM (1580) in Los Angeles, KCAA-AM (1050) in Riverside and San Bernardino, Calif., KPOJ-AM (620) in Portland, Ore., and Channel 167 on XM Satellite Radio.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 6, 2004, Tuesday  A Critic's Notebook article on Thursday about the premiere of the liberal radio network Air America misstated the title given to Al Franken's program, as a parody of Bill O'Reilly's television program on Fox. It is ''The O'Franken Factor,'' not ''The O'Franken Report.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 3, 2004, Saturday</p>
        <p>A Critic's Notebook article on Thursday about the premiere of the liberal radio network Air America omitted the stations on which its programs are heard. They are WLIB-AM (1190) in New York, WNTD-AM (950) in Chicago, KBLA-AM (1580) in Los Angeles, KCAA-AM (1050) in Riverside and San Bernardino, Calif., KPOJ-AM (620) in Portland, Ore., and Channel 167 on XM Satellite Radio.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: April 6, 2004, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A Critic's Notebook article on Thursday about the premiere of the liberal radio network Air America misstated the title given to Al Franken's program, as a parody of Bill O'Reilly's television program on Fox. It is ''The O'Franken Factor,'' not ''The O'Franken Report.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
