<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islamic Art as a Mediator for Cultures in Confrontation</title>
    <meta content="06RIDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/06/arts/design/06RIDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1572081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="An Essay"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4D71E39F935A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islamic Art as a Mediator for Cultures in Confrontation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Islamic Art as a Mediator for Cultures in Confrontation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Riding essay explores question of whether increased appreciation of Islamic art in West can help bridge cultural divide; describes efforts being made to make Islamic art more available in West; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Given the disturbing level of animosity between the West and much of the Islamic world, can increased appreciation of Islamic art in the West help bridge the cultural divide? Is that notion overly optimistic? Perhaps. But since the shock of Sept. 11, 2001, interest in understanding the Islamic world through its art has been growing.</p>
        <p>Certainly, with all the tension caused by the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, the war in Iraq, Al Qaeda and Muslim migration to Europe, probably nothing separates the West and the Islamic world more than cultural misunderstanding. This may not be new, but it can no longer be ignored. And it is too much to expect ''public diplomacy,'' today's euphemism for cultural propaganda, to provide a quick fix.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Interest in understanding the Islamic world through its art has been growing, and museums in Europe are looking to bridge the cultural divide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Given the disturbing level of animosity between the West and much of the Islamic world, can increased appreciation of Islamic art in the West help bridge the cultural divide? Is that notion overly optimistic? Perhaps. But since the shock of Sept. 11, 2001, interest in understanding the Islamic world through its art has been growing.</p>
        <p>Certainly, with all the tension caused by the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, the war in Iraq, Al Qaeda and Muslim migration to Europe, probably nothing separates the West and the Islamic world more than cultural misunderstanding. This may not be new, but it can no longer be ignored. And it is too much to expect ''public diplomacy,'' today's euphemism for cultural propaganda, to provide a quick fix.</p>
        <p>Instead, a case is being made for the benefits of promoting Islamic art in the West: the Islamic world would feel that its heritage was admired in countries that increasingly link Islam with terrorism; Westerners could look beyond today's turmoil to recognize one of the world's great civilizations; and alienated Muslim youths in Europe could identify with the glories of their Islamic roots.</p>
        <p>Thanks to 19th-century explorers and travelers, fine Islamic art collections are plentiful in the West. The Pergamon Museum in Berlin, for instance, has housed a Museum of Islamic Art for more than a century. Yet all too often Islamic art has been hard to find in museums; invariably, it is treated as a poor relative of Egyptian, Greek and Roman antiquities.</p>
        <p>Now, troubled times are changing this.</p>
        <p>In 2002 President Jacques Chirac of France proposed creating a new department of Islamic art in the Louvre to underline ''the essential contribution of Islamic civilizations to our culture.'' Recently, the Louvre announced that a large courtyard would be covered in glass and redesigned to house its Islamic collection, now in underground corridors. The project will cost $60 million and take five years to complete.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, this has a political dimension,'' said the minister of culture, Jean-Jacques Aillagon. ''It's a way of saying we believe in the equality of civilizations.'' He added: ''Many immigrant youths do not fully adhere to our culture, nor do they know their own culture of origin. It's good to show that the republic respects, displays and studies this culture.''</p>
        <p>In London, the Victoria and Albert Museum will present its rich Islamic collection in a spectacular new gallery by 2006, thanks to a $9.7 million gift from Mohammed Jameel, the president of a Saudi business conglomerate. Announcing the gift two months ago, Mr. Jameel said one of his family's objectives was to increase understanding of the Islamic world.</p>
        <p>Mark Jones, the director of the Victoria and Albert, said the new Jameel Gallery of Islamic Art would highlight the diversity of world culture. ''Do we want to confront prejudice?'' he asked. ''Yes, we want to undermine negative attitudes that people bring with them. It's absurd for some people to claim that Islamic culture is a barbaric culture. If you see what there is here, you can't possibly think it is hostile to beauty or education and has no intellectual tradition.''</p>
        <p>While work is under way, the Victoria and Albert will do its own proselytizing by lending 100 of its prized Islamic objects for temporary exhibition at the National Gallery in Washington, the Kimbell Art Museum in Fort Worth, the Setagaya Art Museum in Tokyo and the Millennium Galleries in Sheffield, England. Meanwhile, ''Heaven on Earth: Art From Islamic Lands,'' which presents 60 treasures from the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia, and the Nasser D. Khalili Collection of Islamic Art, is on display at the Hermitage's London home in Somerset House through Aug. 22.</p>
        <p>Temporary shows often create a special buzz. That was the case with ''Islamic Art and Patronage'' from the private collection of Sheik Nasser Sabah al-Ahmed al-Sabah and his wife, Sheika Hussah Sabah al-Salim al-Sabah, who are members of the Kuwaiti royal family. The show traveled to 22 sites around the world and drew large crowds.</p>
        <p>''I'd see a man with a long beard standing next to an elegant lady, sharing a moment,'' Sheika Hussah said. ''Maybe through art we can bring people together.''</p>
        <p>In New York, the Metropolitan Museum of Art's Islamic galleries are closed for renovation. ''Given the present geopolitical situation and increased public interest in Islamic art, this is an unfortunate moment to announce the temporary closing of the Islamic Galleries,'' Philippe de Montebello, the museum's director, conceded last year. But the result, he said, will be to show this art ''side-by-side with related works from other cultures.''</p>
        <p>Like the Louvre and the Victoria and Albert, then, the Met intends to place Islamic art within the context of universal culture. This in turn will help illustrate the influence of Islamic art on architecture and design in the West, most noticeably in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>Some museums, though, have chosen to focus exclusively on Islamic art. One highlight is the new Benaki Museum of Islamic Art in Athens. It is to open in two renovated 19th-century houses in June, in time for the Summer Olympics, displaying an Islamic collection built up by Antonis Benakis in the early 20th century, at the same time that he was building up a treasury of Greek antiquities. ''Greece has always had relations with the Arab world, and it's important to know its art,'' said Mina Moraitou, the collection's curator. ''Islamic art can show the beauty of its art, language and literature, that Islamic religion is not only about jihad.''</p>
        <p>Yet the new interest in Islamic art within the Islamic world is just as important. Cairo and Istanbul have long boasted excellent collections, but a new Museum of Islamic Art, designed by I. M. Pei, is being built in Doha, Qatar. Due to open in 2006, it is the brainchild of Sheik Saud Ibn Muhammad Al Thani, chairman of the National Council of Arts and Heritage, who has been building up Qatar's collection since the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>Oliver Watson, the collection's curator, who is on loan from the Victoria and Albert, underscored the relationship between artistic heritage and the current climate. ''People say that at this moment it is more important to recognize that the Middle East and the Islamic world was in its day as advanced culturally, as well as economically and militarily, as any country or empire in the world,'' he said. Mr. Jones, the Victoria and Albert's director, put it more simply: ''It's no coincidence that people are more interested in Islamic art than ever.''</p>
        <p>An Essay</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
