<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Won't Grow Up. Not Quite Yet, Anyway, if They Can Possibly Help It.</title>
    <meta content="05stan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/05/arts/05stan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1729599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D81130F936A35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Won't Grow Up. Not Quite Yet, Anyway, if They Can Possibly Help It.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They Won't Grow Up. Not Quite Yet, Anyway, if They Can Possibly Help It.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Four Kings,'' an NBC sitcom about four single straight men who share an apartment and a disinclination to grow up, sounds awful. It's not. Some of the dialogue is quite funny, and as a posse, the slacker bachelors are appealing.</p>
        <p>That's mostly because the series was created by Max Mutchnick and David Kohan, the duo behind ''Will &amp; Grace,'' that wicked, madcap look at urban gay life (which could be described as ''Breakfront Mountain'').</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Four Kings" is better than a lot of similar sitcoms, but it's not different enough to stand out in what NBC hopes will be a renaissance of must-see television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Four Kings,'' an NBC sitcom about four single straight men who share an apartment and a disinclination to grow up, sounds awful. It's not. Some of the dialogue is quite funny, and as a posse, the slacker bachelors are appealing.</p>
        <p>That's mostly because the series was created by Max Mutchnick and David Kohan, the duo behind ''Will &amp; Grace,'' that wicked, madcap look at urban gay life (which could be described as ''Breakfront Mountain'').</p>
        <p>NBC hopes ''Four Kings'' will prove wicked and madcap enough about urban heterosexual life to help the network reclaim Thursday nights in a post-''Friends'' era. (The spinoff, ''Joey,'' did not make the cut.) ''Four Kings'' is better than a lot of similar sitcoms, but it's not different enough to stand out in what NBC hopes will be a renaissance of must-see television. The writing is not as clever and high-flown as that of ''Will &amp; Grace,'' and the premise is far more conventional than those of the two new sitcoms that follow, ''My Name Is Earl'' and ''The Office.''</p>
        <p>In its eighth season, ''Will &amp; Grace'' is still funny, but it is on its last legs. ''Four Kings'' is an experiment, a chance to see whether the kind of traditional network sitcom made with four cameras and a laugh track can still attract the younger, sophisticated viewers NBC once owned and operated.</p>
        <p>There are no laugh tracks, musical cues or cute punch lines on either ''Earl'' or ''The Office.'' The style and sensibility of both are distinctive and closer to HBO than to network television. And both move away from urban sophistication to less familiar territory. Jason Lee plays Earl, a backwoods derelict who has an epiphany and decides to improve his karma by undoing past wrongs. It's satire, but softhearted. Mr. Lee is charming, and in Earl's beer-and-trailer-park world, friends, relatives, neighbors and other delinquents form the kind of ersatz extended family that made shows like ''Seinfeld'' and ''Frasier'' such hits.</p>
        <p>''The Office,'' an Americanized version of Ricky Gervais's BBC series, is more pitiless: a mock documentary that is a deadpan parody of workplace mediocrity and tedium. NBC has not always had much luck with knockoffs, but this one works. Steve Carell, who plays Michael, the astoundingly obnoxious, self-deluded boss, has made the character his own, and he is surrounded by a cast of brilliantly awful co-workers who become endearing, but only after a while. For those many viewers who did not see the original on BBC America, the Carell version may seem astonishingly bold.</p>
        <p>''Four Kings'' cannot make the same boast. It's easily summed up as a ''Sex and the City'' for men, or a girl-free ''Friends.'' Sweet-natured Ben (Josh Cooke) inherits his grandmother's vast New York apartment and invites his three oldest and best friends to move in with him -- even though he loses his gorgeous girlfriend in the deal. Ben figures that this is their last chance to be together and backslide.</p>
        <p>''Soon life is going to be about marriages, careers and rehab,'' he explains. ''Let's do this while we still can.''</p>
        <p>Jason (Todd Grinnell) is a former fat kid turned businessman who works out compulsively and also climbs a corporate ladder. Bobby (Shane McRae) is a sweet, dim pothead who will eat anything for a dollar but charges an extra 50 cents ''if it's not food.'' Seth Green, who played Dr. Evil's churlish son in the Austin Powers movies, is Barry, a smart underachiever who is short, paranoid and bitter, particularly about Ben's charmed life.</p>
        <p>The series begins with a flashback to the apartment kitchen when the boys were in elementary school and Ben's grandma fed and nagged them. When she sees Barry holding her silver flask, she demands her perfume bottle back. Barry, already a prematurely angry, needling child, retorts that it's not perfume, it's liquor. ''It's perfume for my heart,'' she explains loftily.</p>
        <p>Their adult predicaments are classic sitcom plotlines. Barry has to baby-sit for his ex-girlfriend's rude, spoiled twins. Ben gets an assignment from Maxim magazine to write about whither the one-night stand and takes his buddies to a hot club frequented by actresses and models. They are wonderstruck. ''There are, like, two girls for every girl,'' Bobby says.</p>
        <p>''Four Kings'' is not misogynistic like ''Two and a Half Men'' on CBS, nor is it as predictable as the mercifully canceled distaff version on ABC, ''Hot Properties.'' The series has grace notes and some wit, but it is also the kind of sitcom that NBC audiences seem to have outgrown. The network must be hoping that viewers will regress right along with the show's characters.</p>
        <p>Four Kings  NBC, tonight at 8:30, Eastern and Pacific times; 7:30, Central time.</p>
        <p>Directed by James Burrows (pilot); David Kohan and Max Mutchnick, creators and executive producers; Tim Kaiser, producer; Bruce Alden, associate producer. A KoMut Entertainment and Warner Brothers Television production.</p>
        <p>WITH: Seth Green (Barry), Josh Cooke (Ben), Todd Grinnell (Jason) and Shane McRae (Bobby).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
